遥远的北方
In the far north,
历经三个月黑暗寒冬之后
after three dark months of winter.
整个世界都在悄然等待
a world is waiting
那一缕春的阳光
..for a trigger.
将其唤醒
The sunshine of spring.
首先回应的是海星
Starfish are the first to respond.
它们奔赴制高点
They race for the highest point...
利用其管足
and sensing changes in the water,
察觉到了水温的变化
with the tips of their tube feet...
它们开始产卵
they spawn.
海参
Sea cucumbers,
原本只露出个嘴巴的它们
with only their mouths exposed,
现在也探出了头
now emerge.
对着海星的卵大快朵颐
They collect as many starfish eggs as they can.
依靠那十只手 还真能吃下不少
Which is quite a lot, when you've got ten arms.
现在海笔也冒出头 想分享大自然的馈赠
Now sea pens rise up to claim a share.
在此年度盛宴上 这里的生物必须努力加餐
The creatures here must grab what they can of this annual banquet.
因为阳光同样预示着一场巨大变革的到来
For the light has also set in motion the greatest transformation of all.
大型褐藻 一种海洋藻类
Fronds of kelp, a marine alga,
拔地而起
rise towards the surface,
它们的气囊协助其向上生长
lifted by their gas-filled bladders.
不久 一片"海底森林"便成形
Soon, a marine forest has materialised...
各种生物在此大量繁衍
teeming with life of all kinds.
绿色海洋是所有水域中最丰饶多产
These green seas are some of the most productive,
而又竞争激烈的
but fiercely competitive, waters in all the oceans.
非洲的最南端
The southern tip of Africa.
两大洋在这里交汇
Here, two great oceans collide.
在浅水区 营养丰富的洋流
In the shallows, fed by rich currents,
滋养了茂盛的海藻林
are bountiful forests of kelp.
几乎只能看见虹吸管一张一合的
Barely visible except for the pulsating siphon through which it breathes,
是一只普通章鱼
a common octopus,
伺机捕捉经过的猎物
waiting for prey to pass by.
一只螃蟹就很不错
A crab will do.
章鱼动身去追赶螃蟹
The octopus sets off in pursuit.
之后潜伏起来
And then lurks.
带着狩猎者与生俱来的沉着
with the patience of an ambush hunter.
但好望角这片海域也同时
But the octopus shares the Cape waters
汇聚了大量其它的捕食者
with a great concentration of other predators.
海狗
Fur seals.
和鲨鱼
and sharks.
而它们的菜谱上都写了章鱼
They all eat octopus.
只要能碰上
if they can find one.
睡袍鲨则是
And pyjama sharks are experts
下层水域的捕猎能手
at hunting in the undergrowth.
是时候该躲起来了
Time to disappear.
但这些皮肤坚硬的小鲨鱼
But these tough-skinned little sharks
体型恰好可以深入裂缝中
are small enough to reach deep into crevices.
但是章鱼可不会轻易认输
But the octopus is far from finished.
它把触角滑进鲨鱼的鳃里
She slips her tentacles into the shark's gills.
阻止其呼吸
That prevents the shark from breathing.
最终后者不得不放弃
So, the shark has to let go.
当章鱼无处藏匿极为脆弱时
When caught out in the open, and vulnerable,
同样可以做出一些令人惊讶
this octopus does something truly extraordinary.
闻所未闻的举动
and never recorded before.
它做了一个贝壳盔甲
She disguises herself
来伪装自己
with a protective armour of shells.
她就躲避在敌人的视线之下
She's hiding...in plain sight.
鲨鱼可以察觉到猎物
The shark can sense its prey
但是贝壳迷惑了它
but the shells confuse it.
在一个满是饥饿猎食者的森林里
In a forest full of hungry mouths,
章鱼因它卓越的智慧而幸存
superior wits allow this octopus to stay alive.
海藻森林在全世界季节性海域中繁荣生长
Forests of kelp flourish in seasonal waters around the globe...
尤其是北美的太平洋沿岸
particularly along the Pacific Coast of North America.
在这里 海藻森林中
Here, the biggest kelps of all
生长着最大的藻类
grow in vast forests,
可以延伸到几百英里之外
stretching for hundreds of miles.
一些地区 那些巨藻
In some places, the giant fronds
可以长到60米
rise up to 60 metres tall.
茂盛的丛林中 生物繁多
The thickets they create are crowded with life.
在这里 空间和食物的竞争异常激烈
Competition here, for space and food, is intense.
这对于美国红雀来说可是个大难题
A challenging problem for the Garibaldi fish.
它仔细照料自己的海藻地
He tends to his patch of seaweed,
里面充满了它爱吃的小生物
filled with tiny creatures that he eats.
和大多数农民一样 他一天到晚辛勤劳动
As with most farmers, his work never ends.
它把海螺和其他一些
He removes snails and any other grazers
吃他海藻的动物赶走
that come to eat his algae
不管对方有多庞大
no matter how big they are.
它必须处理所有的"害虫"
He has to deal with pests of all kinds.
这是最难处理的家伙
This can be the worst of them -
海胆会把岩石上的海藻刮得一干二净
sea urchins that can scrape off every vestige of algae from a rock.
它们的刺像针一样锋利
Its spines are needle-sharp.
雀鲷必须把它移走
Somehow, the GaribaldI must remove it.
但问题是
But the problem with sea urchins
海胆会不停的聚集过来
is that they just keep coming.
当日渐西斜 夜晚来临 小雀鲷不得不停下
When evening arrives and the light fades, he has to stop.
它不仅需要休息 还需要躲藏
He not only needs a rest, he needs to hide.
因为在晚上 捕猎者会穿梭在森林中觅食
Because at night, predators prowl through these forests.
电鳐
A torpedo ray,
能用45伏特的电压 把猎物电晕
capable of stunning its victim with 45 volts of electricity.
当雀鲷躲起来时
While the Garibaldi hides...
海胆又能肆无忌惮的吃海藻了
the urchins can feed without interruption.
白天来临
The light returns...
它发现自己的农田又一次遭到破坏
and he finds his farm is once again under attack.
海胆就像蝗虫
Urchins, like locusts,
总是蜂拥而至
have the ability to swarm.
这会是一个大灾难 不仅是对雀鲷来说
And this can be disastrous, not just for the Garibaldi,
更是对整个海藻森林
but for the kelp forest itself.
现在所有的植物都遭到破坏
All the vegetation is now under attack.
海胆在森林里
The urchins move through the forest,
肆虐横行
cutting through the kelp fronds
留下一片狼藉
and leaving behind vast barrens.
这些海胆军团曾袭击过
These urchin armies have felled many kelp forests
北美洲太平洋沿岸的许多海藻森林
along the Pacific Coast of North America.
但是救兵顷刻将至
But help is at hand.
海獭
Sea otters.
其他水獭大多常年生活在陆地上
All other kinds of otters spend much of their lives on land,
但海獭却很少离开水
but sea otters rarely leave the water.
一开始 新生的小海獭还不怎么会游泳
At first, a newly-born pup is not a very good swimmer,
水獭妈妈会花数个小时帮宝宝梳理毛发 好让它浮起来
so its mother spends hours grooming its fur to make it buoyant.
水獭妈妈为了给孩子喂奶 并保持自身体温
But to provide her youngster with milk and keep herself warm,
每天必须吃掉相当于其体重30%的食物
she must eat up to 30% of her body weight every day.
贝类是她的家常菜
She does that by eating shellfish.
而海胆则是海獭的最爱
And urchins are among a sea otter's favourite delicacies.
过去 人们为了海獭的毛皮对其肆意捕杀
In the past, sea otters were hunted so intensively for their fur
使它们濒临灭绝
that they came close to extinction.
海獭数量减少 海藻森林则被海胆占领 留下大片荒凉
With them gone, many kelp forests were replaced with urchin barrens.
现在 海獭被保护起来
Today, sea otters are protected...
随着它们数量的缓慢回升
and as their numbers slowly return,
许多海藻森林也在恢复
many of the kelp forests are recovering, too.
现在 一些偏远地区
Now, in some remote places,
生活着大量海獭
sea otters are so numerous
它们汇聚成一个个巨型筏子
they assemble in huge rafts...
类似的场景已经上百年未曾见过
something that hasn't been seen for over a century.
在澳洲阳光充足的浅水区
In the sun-drenched shallows off Australia...
生长的不是海藻 而是海上唯一的开花植物
kelp is replaced by the sea's only flowering plants,
海草
sea grass.
最广阔的海洋草地
The most extensive of these marine grasslands
能衍延伸3000多平方英里
can stretch for over 3,000 square miles.
整片热带区域 都由虎鲨巡逻着
All across the tropics, they're patrolled by tiger sharks.
它们能长到5米长
They can grow up to five metres in length...
拥有可以撕开猎物的强大双颚
and have powerful crushing jaws.
绿海龟是它们的食物
Green turtles are their prey.
海龟几乎完全以海草为生
The turtles feed almost entirely on sea grass.
一只海龟每天能消耗2公斤海草
A single one can consume up to two kilos of it in a day.
但它们从来不得安生
But they can never rest easy.
健康的海龟会避开接近的鲨鱼
Healthy turtles will keep well away from an approaching shark.
通过使海龟的不停移动
And just by keeping the turtles on the move,
鲨鱼便防止了海草被过度破坏
the sharks prevent any one patch of sea grass from being overgrazed.
这对大家都有利
And that has benefits for us all.
与同面积的热带雨林相比
A patch of sea grass can absorb and store
海草能吸收并储存
35 times as much carbon dioxide
雨林35倍的二氧化碳
as the same area of a rainforest.
所以 这片草甸与鲨鱼们
So, the prairies and their sharks
在对抗全球变暖的斗争中成了盟友
are surprising allies in the fight against a warming climate.
绿海图存的斗争
The struggle to survive in our green seas
可能带来尤为深远的影响
can have far-reaching consequences.
每年 澳洲的这片特殊草原 都在变化
Once a year, one particular meadow in Australia is transformed.
在冬季的首个满月前后
Around the first full moon of winter,
一支军队逐渐集结
an army materialises.
蜘蛛蟹
Spider crabs.
过去的一年里 他们都在深海区觅食
For the past year, they've been feeding in deeper waters.
现在 他们要穿过这片海上草原
Now they march across the sea-grass plains.
数量可达几十万
Hundreds of thousands of them.
一个个叠在一起
They clamber over one another...
形成一个巨大的山丘
creating great mounds...
绵延近百米
nearly 100 metres long.
它们不是在寻找配偶 也不是在产卵
They're not seeking mates, neither are they laying eggs.
而是为了
They have come here in order...
成长
to grow.
像其他螃蟹一样
Like all crabs,
他们的身体被封闭在
their bodies are enclosed
坚硬 不能伸缩的壳里面
in a hard, un-expandable shell.
所以 为了成长 必须打破硬壳
So, to grow, they have to break out of it...
这样才能使硬壳之下的柔软新壳长大
and that allows the soft one that has developed beneath to expand.
新壳需要数天才能变硬
It will take days for the new shell to harden.
这时 它们的腿疲软无力 不能灵活行动
Its legs are so limp that they won't work properly.
蜘蛛蟹失去保护外壳 极为脆弱
The crab is unprotected and in great danger.
刺魟
A smooth stingray.
体型巨大 长达四米
It's huge - about four metres long.
它想抓住只柔软 刚蜕壳的蜘蛛蟹
It wants a soft, freshly-moulted crab
这种食物更好下口
that will be easier to eat.
蜘蛛蟹努力 聚到一起
The crabs try to stick together.
但现在被刺魟分散开
But now, disturbed by the ray,
四散奔逃
they're scattering.
一只刚蜕壳的蜘蛛蟹
A newly-moulted crab
因为太虚弱 跟不上群体
is too weak to keep up with the crowd.
最安全的地方是蟹群的中央
The safest place is right in the middle of the pile.
这也是它们聚集在一起的原因
That is why they have all assembled here.
数量越多 越安全
There is safety in numbers.
绝大多数的蜘蛛蟹能够逃脱
The vast majority of the crabs escape...
几天过后
and within the next few days,
它们就准备回归深海
they will be ready to return to the depths
重新开始流浪般的孤独觅食
and resume their lonely wanderings in search of food.
这不是一片墓地
This is no graveyard...
而是十万多只蜘蛛蟹蜕壳成功的胜利标志
..but the triumph of a 100,000 crabs successfully moulted.
在澳大利亚南部的绿色海洋
The green seas of Southern Australia
类似壮观的聚集十分多
are particularly rich in such spectacular assemblies...
但是大多数物种聚集起来
..but most of the creatures come together
是为了一件截然不同的事情
for a very different reason.
交配繁殖
To breed.
澳大利亚巨型乌贼
The giant cuttlefish,
体型最大的乌贼
the largest of all cuttlefish.
生命周期只有一到两年
They live for just one or two years.
随着澳大利亚的夏季即将结束
Now, as the Australian summer draws to an end,
它们还有最后一件事情需要完成
they have one last act to complete.
求偶
To find a mate.
在这一个海湾里 就有超过10万只雄性乌贼
But there are over 100,000 males,
准备争夺即将到来的雌性乌贼
competing for the arriving females in this one bay.
他们之中有一个名副其实的歌利亚
Among them a giant - a true Goliath.
体重大概有10公斤
He probably weighs about ten kilos.
皮肤上色彩绚丽的带状花纹
Bands of colour sweep across his skin.
正是乌贼的交流方式
That's how cuttlefish communicate.
这只体型较小的雄性乌贼显然难以与之匹敌
This smaller male couldn't possibly take him on.
在歌利亚身旁 其庇护之下
Beside Goliath, and under his protection,
一只雌性乌贼刚刚与它交配完
a female who has just mated with him.
但其它竞争者仍旧蠢蠢欲动
But other rivals are still interested.
看来小个头的雄性是毫无胜算的
It seems a small male wouldn't stand a chance.
雌性乌贼朝着歌利亚一侧的身体上
The female is now displaying a white stripe
显出了白色条纹
along her side nearest Goliath.
这是个明显的信号 她不想与其交配了
It's a clear signal that she no longer wants to mate with him.
这条小型雄乌贼又重拾了希望
It's all the encouragement that the little male needs.
它打算耍个花招
He's going to have to use trickery.
把自己表皮的颜色变暗
He tones down his colours
蜷缩起它的触手
and tucks in his arms.
他模仿成雌性乌贼大小
He's just the right size to mimic a female.
歌利亚上当了
Goliath is deceived.
这头小型雄性乌贼的身上也出现了白色条纹
The small male now displays a white stripe,
就像真正的雌性一样  这是为了阻止歌利亚靠近自己
just like the real female, to deter his advances.
它溜到她身边
He slips beside her...
然后和她交配
..and they mate.
通过与多个伴侣交配
By mating with multiple partners...
雌性乌贼能够最大程度上确保其后代遗传基因的多样性
..the female ensures the greatest genetic diversity for her young.
这个狡猾的雄性离开了
The sneaky male leaves,
他已完成了终极目标
his final act complete.
所以 即使是在巨型乌贼当中
So, even among giant cuttlefish, it seems...
个头也并不总是能决定一切
..it's not all about size.
另一些居住在这片澳大利亚绿色海草里的雄性生物
Other males in these Australian green pastures,
则要为它们的后代承担更重大的责任
take greater responsibility for their young.
一只草海龙
A weedy sea dragon.
这是只雄性海龙 它正身负重任
This is a male and he's carrying a precious cargo.
在与雌性进行交配时
While mating with the female,
他会收集雌性所产的卵 并将它们附在自己身体下部
he collected the eggs and attached them to his underside.
现在 他正要离开这片海草丛
Now, he's leaving these seaweed thickets...
前往更开阔的水域
..and travelling into more open waters
在那里几乎无处藏身
where elaborate camouflage is less effective.
并且有诸多的捕食者
And there are many predators out here.
而这便是海龙爸爸不惜以身犯险的理由
And this is what the fathers risk their lives for.
多如烟云般的小虾
Dense clouds of minute shrimp.
糠虾 海龙最喜欢的食物之一
Mysids, one of a sea dragon's favourite foods.
这也引来了其它的海龙
They're drawing other sea dragons out here, too.
终于 小家伙们该出世了
Finally, it's time for the young to break free.
但水藻覆满了这些正在成长的卵
But algae has grown over these developing eggs...
这会让它们有窒息的风险
..and it risks smothering them.
然而 小宝宝们还是顺利降生
Nonetheless, the babies are emerging.
它们成功地孵化了
They've hatched successfully.
父亲们回到了巨大的海藻丛中
The fathers return to the tangle of kelp,
在那里可以很好地隐藏自己
where they're virtually invisible...
年幼的海龙继续留在那
..while the young remain out here.
被钟爱的食物所环绕
But they will grow quickly,
它们很快便能长大
surrounded as they are by their ideal food.
为数众多的小型鱼类
Vast numbers of the oceans' young fish
早期都生活在这片绿色海洋里
start their lives in the green seas.
而红树林当属其中最为富饶的水域
One of the richest nurseries of all are the mangrove forests.
沿着热带地区海岸线边缘生长
Fringing the coastline of the tropics,
它们在陆地与海洋之间建立了一个天然的保护屏障
they form a natural protective barrier between land and sea...
同时也是世界上最丰富多产的森林
..and are some of the world's most productive forests.
在水面之下 拱状的树根
Below the water, their arching aerial roots
赋予他们扎实的底子
give them a firm footing.
这里能够为幼鱼提供充足的食物
Here, there's abundant food for baby fish.
盘根错节保护它们不受大型鱼类
While the tangled roots protect them from bigger fish
以及其他捕食者们的纠缠
and other predators that haunt the channels.
但在澳大利亚北部
But in Northern Australia,
随着潮水退去
with the receding tide...
小型鱼类不得不离开它们的庇护所
..the little fish are forced to leave their shelter.
现在 它们变得十分脆弱
And now, they are vulnerable.
这是绿色海洋里最为致命的杀手
It's the most deadly assassin in the green seas.
斑马纹螳螂虾
The zebra mantis shrimp,
一只雄性虾蛄 大约四十厘米长
a male, almost 40 centimetres long.
但它捕猎并不只是为了自己
But he's not hunting just for himself.
它在为自己的伴侣搜集食物
He's collecting food for his mate.
双方在一起已经近二十年了
She may have been his partner for 20 years.
她依靠雄虾为自己带来食物
She relies on him to bring her food...
这样她才能有力气生儿育女
..and puts her energy into her eggs instead.
在这个食物充足的世界里
In a world so full of food,
这种方法显得合情合理
this would seem a sensible strategy.
但同时也极为冒险
But it's also a risky one.
如果她的雄性伴侣消失不见
Were her male to disappear,
她可能会饿死
she could starve.
有什么东西引起了雄性虾蛄的注意
Something has caught this male's attention.
也许是猎物令人无法抗拒的气味
Perhaps an irresistible odour...
又或许是一声遥远的呼唤
..or a distant call.
不管那是什么
Whatever the reason,
这只雄性虾蛄都要离开自己的洞穴
a male will leave his burrow
和它那约定终身的伴侣
and his lifelong mate.
(前往)一个更大的洞穴
An even larger hole.
雌性虾蛄在失去伴侣之后
Females who have lost their mates
会发出求救信号 召唤新的伴侣
appear to send out distress signals to call in a new male.
体型更大的雌性虾蛄会产更多的卵
A larger female will produce more eggs.
如果和她交配 这只雄性虾蛄会有更多的后代
So by mating with her, he will father more offspring.
但出轨是要付出代价的
But infidelity comes at a price.
更大的伴侣其食欲自然也更大
A larger partner demands more food.
海洋越是富饶 那里的竞争也就越激烈
The richer a sea, the greater the competition.
而这里有一片绿色海洋
...and there is one green sea
比其他所有海洋联合起来养育的生命还要多
that supports more life than all the rest combined.
不同于红树林和海草原
Unlike the mangrove forests and the sea-grass prairies,
它坐落在外海
its location is in the open seas
时间短暂且不可预知
and only temporary and unpredictable.
这片绿意不是来自于生根植物
This greenness comes not from rooted plants...
而是来自成群的浮游生物
..but from clouds of floating ones.
亿万浮游生物正在分裂繁殖
Billions of microscopic phytoplankton are proliferating.
它们在为最盛大的宴会提供养料
And in such numbers that they fuel one of the greatest feasts of all.
在美国太平洋海岸区外
Off America's Pacific Coast,
几百只普通海豚正赶着赴宴
hundreds of common dolphins are rushing to a banquet.
它们不是唯一赶去的生物
They're not the only ones homing in.
海狮亦是如此
So are sea lions.
它们要前往加利福尼亚州蒙特雷湾
They're heading for Monterey Bay, California,
那里藻类植物繁茂 导致浮游生物
where algal blooms have caused an explosion
呈爆炸式生长
in plankton feeders.
凤尾鱼 百万雄军
Anchovies, millions of them.
海豚把凤尾鱼赶向海水表面
The dolphins herd the anchovies towards the surface.
海鸟和海狮从中占得便宜
Sea birds and sea lions take advantage of the shoal's appearance.
大家都抢着在其他生物到来之前分一杯羹
It's a race to grab a share before others arrive.
座头鲸
Humpback whales,
共有好几百头
hundreds of them.
每向上张开一次血盆大口
With every upward lunge,
它们都能筛出100多公斤的鱼
they sieve out up to 100 kilos of fish.
它们从最大的一场盛宴中
They're  claiming the biggest share
拿走了最丰厚的一份
of one of the biggest feasts on Earth.
这些微小的浮游生物至关重要
So crucial are these tiny plankton,
因为几乎所有的海洋生物都赖以生存
that almost all marine life ultimately depends upon them.
绿色的海洋 而非蓝色
It's the green seas, not the blue...
才是世界海洋之中所有生命的基础
..that are the basis of almost all life in the world's oceans.
为了捕捉到海底森林的壮美景色
To capture the magnificence of the undersea forests
以及生活在其中的令人惊奇的生物
and the surprising creatures living here,
蓝色星球Ⅱ的团队开发了一系列专业摄影器械
the Blue Planet II team have developed a series of specialist camera rigs.
从巨型拱顶摄像机 可以在树冠层捕捉
From the mega-dome recording half-in-half-out shots
一半水面一半水下的镜头
at the top of the towering canopy...
到最先进的延时设备
..to state-of-the-art time-lapse equipment
去发现海底森林里最隐秘的生命
that speeds up time to reveal the secret life of the forest floor.
不过 在所有水下生命拍摄中
But, of all the creatures living in these forests,
在南非好望角水域的取材
filming one in the waters off the Cape of South Africa
被认作是最艰巨的挑战
was to prove the greatest challenge of all.
自然学家克雷格 福斯特对那里最为神秘的居民
Naturalist Craig Foster has developed a fascination
产生了浓厚兴趣 一只普通章鱼
for its most secretive resident, a common octopus.
这片水域中生活着大概100种鲨鱼
There are almost 100 species of shark in these waters,
但克雷格没有被吓倒
but that doesn't deter Craig,
在过去的六年里 他每天清晨都到这里游泳
who's swum here every morning for the past six years.
如果你能够找到这种极为微小的椭圆形空洞
When you find that really small, tiny, little oval hole,
就说明它是被一只章鱼杀死的
then you know it's been killed by an octopus.
如果你再仔细进行观察
And then if you look very, very carefully,
就会发现它们经常在附近徘徊
they're often in the vicinity of that.
克雷格见过这些章鱼的滑稽举动
Craig has witnessed the antics of these octopuses
他很想把这种了不起的发现
and wants to share his remarkable discoveries
与蓝色星球的摄影师罗杰 霍洛克斯分享
with Blue Planet cameraman Roger Horrocks.
罗杰很快就被这些家伙鲜明的个性迷住了
Roger is immediately charmed by the strength of their personalities.
看到这些生物都有着各自的特性真是相当令人惊讶
It's really been astounding to see how individual these characters are.
每一只章鱼都展现出了不同的行为举止
The common octopus all display different behaviours.
有些章鱼胆小如鼠
Some were extremely timid,
有些则胆大包天
some were very, very bold,
它们的个性多种多样 我非常喜欢它们
they have variety and it's really endeared me to them.
摄影师不停拍摄各类章鱼 几周之后
After weeks of filming different individuals,
他们终于遇见了一只章鱼
they finally meet one octopus
她看起来并不害怕摄像机
that's not only seemingly unafraid of the camera,
反倒愿意主动靠近
but willing to perform for it.
她就直接这么过来了
She just came right up - whoop!
然后直接穿过我两腿之间的三脚架
And then came right through underneath the tripod in between my legs.
是吧 她很酷 很了不起
Yeah, that's cool, amazing.
她很快就全盘接受了我们俩
She very quickly just completely accepted both of us.
我们实际上已经做出了一些非常亲密的行为
So, we've actually been getting these really intimate behaviours.
令人惊叹
It's amazing.
我已经观察这只章鱼好几个月了
I've watched this octopus for many months,
在水下她一直很信任我们
it's just trusting us in the water,
她一直正常活动 这真是太棒了
carrying on with normal activity which is just so fantastic.
几个月后 团队终于拍到了这只明星章鱼狩猎的情景
Months later, the team finally film their star octopus on the hunt.
然而接下来 他们便发现占有这片海底深林的
But then discover the grave consequences of sharing the forest
并不只有章鱼
with so many other predators -
睡袍鲨
pyjama sharks.
一般情况下 这种鲨鱼比大白鲨
Pound for pound, these sharks are far more brazen
更为凶狠好斗
and aggressive than a Great White.
它们就像导弹
They're like guided missiles.
即使章鱼只留下一点点气味 睡袍鲨都能找到它
The slightest smell that octopus gives off, that shark will find it.
这只睡袍鲨实际上已经抓住了那只章鱼
The pyjama shark actually got hold of the octopus
我当时以为她肯定完了
and, I mean, I just assumed that was it.
与她长时间相处后
After spending so much time with this animal,
你很难真正无动于衷
it was just so difficult watching her get attacked.
之后令他们意想不到的是 她居然反击了
Then, to their amazement, she fights back!
她伸出自己的触手
She put her tentacles down,
你能看见她把触手伸到鲨鱼的鳃里
you can see them coming through the gill, basically,
堵住了鲨鱼的嘴 鲨鱼不能呼吸了
closed the mouth. The shark couldn't breathe,
只能放她离开
and that's what enabled her to escape.
我们亲眼见证整个过程
And just witnessing that whole thing was,
那是生死攸关的时刻
you know, it was an incredibly intense moment.
整个团队都因她逃走而松了一口气
The team are relieved by her escape.
但当她在开阔的水域被发现时
But when caught out in the open,
接下来的把戏更加令他们感到震惊
her next trick astonishes them even more.
她将全身蜷缩起来
It lifted its arms and legs over its head,
并把一些贝壳覆盖在身上
and, at the same time, pulled the shell material with it
做成了这个超凡的盔甲
and created this extraordinary armoury.
她武装好自己之后 那只鲨鱼
Octopus had armoured up and then, when that guy came
自后面赶来 他能闻到一些气息
through from the back, he could kind of smell something.
但没有看见章鱼
He's not seeing an octopus shape,
而是看见这个奇怪的东西
he's seeing that strange armoury.
接着他去碰撞这只章鱼
Then he was bumping the octopus,
看着这只章鱼如何利用自己的盔甲
and it was just incredible to see how that octopus
和智慧去战胜那只鲨鱼
outwitted that shark using the armour,
简直不可思议
using all it's, it's knowledge,
这是一场相当精彩的表演
it's just...absolutely phenomenal.
她是个摇滚巨星 一个真正的摇滚巨星
She's a rock star, man. A proper little rock star.
感谢克雷格和罗杰的奉献精神
Thanks to Craig's and Roger's dedication,
现在科学界终于了解到了章鱼那不为人知的秘密
the octopuses' astonishing behaviours are now known to science.
随着对海底森林的持续探索
What else might we find as we continue to explore
我们还会发现什么呢
these fascinating undersea forests?
下期蓝色星球Ⅱ
Next time on Blue Planet II...
我们将与那些生活在两个世界交界处的生物们见面
we meet the creatures that live where two worlds collide...
并探索它们将如何应对
..and discover how they cope with the demands
海岸线的变化多端
of the ever-changing coasts.
Translated by
YOUNGER & GRAPES
翻译：Younger & 葡萄
Supervised by
VERONICA
监制：斑斑
Proofreaded by
LONG & WILDER
校对：小龙 & 歪二德
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SHOU
特效：歪二德
绿   色   海   洋
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(普通章鱼:章鱼科 章鱼属下的一个物种)
(睡袍鲨学名带纹长须猫鲨,南非沿海水域的特有物种)
(管足:棘皮动物水管系统中从辐管分出的管状运动器官,也可作呼吸和感觉器官)
(学名海鳃,是成千上万水螅体组成的群落,能发磷光,中央茎由初级水螅体构成)
(通过非洲大陆南端[厄加勒斯角]的东经20°线至南极大陆是大西洋与印度洋的分界线)
(章鱼虹吸管用于呼吸 废物处理和排放墨水)
(美国红雀为特大号雀鲷鱼,寿命很长,有记载可以活25年)
蜘蛛蟹蟹壳上的凸起圆球是附着的海葵,双方为共生关系
蜘蛛蟹用海葵分泌的毒液保护自己,其爬行又给海葵捕食提供了方便
(此为澳大利亚著名景点 十二使徒岩 位于坎贝尔港国家公园之中)
(学名伞膜乌贼, 触须50厘米,全长超过100厘米,重量可达10公斤以上)
(歌利亚:《圣经》中的巨人勇士,带兵进攻以色列军队,拥有无穷的力量)
【海龙与海马的区别】
(海龙的身体比海马大,且海龙头部和身体有叶状附肢,尾巴也不像海马的可以盘卷起来)
(学名斑琴虾蛄,皮皮虾的一种,是已知现存体型最大的虾蛄,肉质鲜甜嫩滑,味美可口)
(普通海豚又名短吻真海豚, 是海豚科真海豚属下的动物)
(附着在鲸体表的是鲸藤壶和鲸虱,白环是鲸藤壶脱落后留下的疤痕)